Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.12
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dick Thornburgh Papers, Series XII. Director, Institute of Politics, John F. Kennedy School of Government, Harvard University
1987-1988
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thornburgh, Dick
AIS.1998.30.12
36.25 Linear Feet
Dick Thornburgh became Director of Harvard's Institute of Politics (IOP) in June 1987 and held this position until he was unexpectedly named Attorney General of the United States by President Reagan in July 1988. Thornburgh was the first IOP director who had been an elected public official and enjoyed the opportunity to encourage students to consider careers in politics and government. During his time with IOP, Thornburgh served as an advisor to students, selected and arranged for Institute Fellows, initiated fundraising for programs, wrote articles, in addition to planning IOP workshops, programs and conferences. Also here are other materials relating to Thornburgh's board of trustees positions and concurrently his association with his law firm, Kirkpatrick and Lockhart. Within this series are Ginny Thornburgh's files as Harvard's Coordinator of Programs for Persons with Disabilities. There are twelve sections of files: Speeches; Pre Directorship IOP research; News Releases; Harvard, John F. Kennedy School and IOP; Director's Files; Events; Schedules; Correspondence; Clippings and Articles; Boards and Memberships; Kirkpatrick and Lockhart; and Ginny Thornburgh at Harvard. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dick Thornburgh, February 27, 1998.
Previous Citation
Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932-, AIS.1998.30, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Pennsylvania -- Economic conditions; Government; Economic development projects -- Pennsylvania; Politics; Personal papers; Education; Business and Industry; Harvard University; John F. Kennedy School of Government. Institute of Politics; Kirkpatrick & Lockhart; Thornburgh, Ginny (Judson); Thornburgh, Dick
- Director, Institute of Politics, John F. Kennedy School of Government, Harvard University, 1987-1988; XII.
  Scope and Contents note
  Thornburgh served as the Director of the Institute of Politics at Harvard University's John F. Kennedy School of Government from June of 1987 until August of 1988. When unexpectedly named Attorney General of the United States by President Reagan in July 1988, he resigned after but one year in Boston.
  As Thornburgh's second term as Governor of Pennsylvania was coming to an end, Thornburgh was faced with the necessity of finding a job, since Pennsylvania law limits Governors to two four-year terms. The task, as it turned out, was not a difficult one as Thornburgh received three notable opportunities. U.S. Secretary of State George Shultz asked him to become the administrator of the Agency of International Development (AID) and U.S. Attorney General Edwin Meese asked him to be director of the FBI. Thornburgh turned down both of these offers stating, "I had no strong desire to take on the important AID responsibility toward the end of the Reagan administration, and the ten-year term of the FBI appointment called for a commitment I was not ready to make" (Evidence, p. 196).
  The third opportunity presented an intriguing prospect for Thornburgh and was the offer he ultimately accepted. In November 1986 he had attended a conference at the Institute of Politics (IOP) at Harvard University's John F. Kennedy School of Government. He shortly thereafter received a call from retiring director Jonathan Moore during which Thornburgh was asked if he was interested in the directorship. He was interviewed and subsequently named director in January 1987. The announcement of his appointment called Thornburgh "a very successful governor and practicing politician who, like President John F. Kennedy, whom the Institute memorializes, has a deep personal commitment to public life and government as a high calling." After moving to Boston to take on this new position, he also rejoined his former law firm, Kirkpatrick and Lockhart, which had opened an office in Boston.
  IOP, for Thornburgh, was a "unique and fascinating place" (Evidence, p. 197). It gave him a chance, as the first director that had been an elected public official, to encourage students to consider careers in politics and government. As he told the Harvard University Gazette in an introductory interview, he could "instill in students more enthusiasm for the electoral process and a recognition that 'holding public office ... is an honorable profession'... If during my tenure here I can divert a dozen or so of the best and brightest Harvard students from careers in investment banking into the electoral process, I'd consider it a job well done" (Evidence, p. 197).
  Thornburgh was involved in all facets of IOP including serving as advisor to students, selecting and arranging for Institute Fellows each semester, initiating fundraising for programs, writing articles, in addition to planning IOP workshops, programs and conferences. The files include: speeches, pre-Directorship research about IOP, news releases, Thornburgh's director files, events and schedules, correspondence, clippings and articles.
  In addition to these specific IOP files researchers should note that we have other material from the same year in time although not directly related to IOP. There are files relating to Thornburgh's boards of trustees positions and concurrently his association with his law firm, Kirkpatrick and Lockhart during this same year in Boston. Here as well are files about Ginny Thornburgh's work at Harvard as Coordinator of Programs for Persons with Disabilities. These files are related to the IOP files only in that they were produced in the same short time period, making it relevant to group these separate yet simultaneously produced materials together.
  There are twelve sections here: Speeches; Pre Directorship IOP research; News Releases; Harvard, John F. Kennedy School and IOP; Director's Files; Events; Schedules; Correspondence; Clippings and Articles; Boards and Memberships; Kirkpatrick and Lockhart; and Ginny Thornburgh at Harvard.
  - Speeches, 1.
    As Director of the Institute of Politics, Thornburgh's speeches have been preserved and digitized, as is true for all the positions he has held. These files not only contain the speeches but any drafts and additional notes that may exist. In their digital state the speeches are searchable online for topics of interest and provide invaluable content related to the issues with which Thornburgh was involved during this year from June 1987 through July 1988.
    - "A Revitalized Concept of Public Service," Spring Meeting of the National Academy of Public Administration, Philadelphia, PA, June 4, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 1)
    - "Responsibilities, Opportunities ... and Love," Harrisburg Academy Commencement, Wormleysburg, PA, June 10, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 2)
    - "The Republican Message: Principles to Serve our Nation," Ohio League of Young Republicans, Dayton, OH, August 1, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 3)
    - "Reflections on Governing: Some Principles of Leadership," Annual Conference of Governmental Research Association, Boston, MA, August 18, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 4)
    - "Jobs and Competition in the 1980s," Southern Republican Exchange, Columbia, SC, August 22, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 5)
    - "Republicans and the Constitution: Principles to Serve our Nation," Pennsylvania Republican Leadership Council, Philadelphia, PA, September 26, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 6)
    - Testimony of Dick Thornburgh Before the Judiciary Committee of the United States Senate, September 28, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 7)
    - Presidential Campaign Question and Answer, September, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 8)
    - "Reflections on Governing: Some Principles of Leadership," Board of Trustees of Florida Taxwatch, Inc., Tallahassee, FL, October 14, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 9)
    - "Reflections on Governing: Some Principles on Leadership," 1987 Human Resource Management Conference, West Virginia Chapter International Personnel Management Association, Morgantown, WV, November 2, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 10)
    - "Reflections on Governing: Some Principles of Leadership," Management Education Leadership Program of Digital Equipment Corporation, Bedford, MA, November 5, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 11)
    - "The Three Mile Island Experience: Ten Lessons in Emergency Management," A Conference on Energy Strategies in the Northeast, Cambridge, MA, November 6, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 12)
    - "The Republican Message: Principles to Serve our Nation," Illinois Republican Party, Peoria, IL, November 7, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 13)
    - "The State's Role in an Era of Economic Transition: The Pennsylvania Experience," The Public Management Club of Harvard Business School, Cambridge, MA, November 9, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 14)
    - 93rd Annual Meeting of the National Civic League, Inc., Boston, MA, November 16, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 15)
    - "A Revitalized Concept of Public Service," 68th Annual Dinner of the Children's Welfare Association, Erie, PA, December 6, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 16)
    - "Responsibilities and Opportunities ... Beginning the Journey," A Graduation Address to the Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, December 13, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 17)
    - "Wanted: An Environment For Jobs and Economic Growth for America," Pittsburgh Rotary Club, Pittsburgh, PA, January 27, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 18)
    - "The Republican Message: Principles to Serve our Nation," Lincoln Day Dinner of the Idaho Republican Party, Boise, ID, February 11, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 19)
    - "Reflections on Governing: Some Principles of Leadership," 18th Annual County Government Officials Conference, Center for Governmental Services, Auburn University, Auburn, AL, February 18, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 20)
    - Service of Morning Prayers at the Memorial Church, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA, February 23, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 21)
    - "The Three Mile Island Experience: Ten Lessons in Emergency Management," Seminar on Command Control, Communication, and Intelligence, John F. Kennedy School of Government, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA, February 25, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 22)
    - "The Republican Message: Principles to Serve Our Nation," Lincoln Club of Orange County, Irvine, CA, March 7, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 23)
    - "Challenges Facing State and Local Governments: The National Picture," Keynote Speech to 'Preparing for the Year 2000: Future Policy Directions for Florida,' Conference Sponsored by Florida International University, North Miami Campus, Miami, FL, March 18, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 24)
    - "A Revitalized Concept of Public Service," Centennial Banquet of Pennsylvania Society of the Sons of the Revolution, Union League of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, PA, March 19, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 25)
    - "Educating for Expanding Horizons in a Shrinking World: An Agenda for the Future," Paul H. Masoner Education Lecture, University of Pittsburgh School of Education, Pittsburgh, PA, March 22, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 26)
    - "The State's Role in an Era of Economic Transition: The Pennsylvania Experience," Annual Conference of the National Conference For Urban Economic Development, Washington, DC, April 11, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 27)
    - Chicago Tribune Charity Dinner, Chicago, IL, April 15, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 28)
    - "Responsibilities and Opportunities ... Beginning the Journey," A Graduation Address to York College of Pennsylvania, York, PA (with draft), May 14, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 29)
    - NAACP Legal Defense and Education Fund, Annual Civil Rights Institute to Commemorate the 34th Anniversary of Brown v. Board of Education, New York, NY, May 17, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 30)
    - "Jobs and Economic Growth: Dealing with the Threat of the Federal Deficit," Annual Dinner of the Allentown-Lehigh County Chamber of Commerce, Allentown, PA, May 18, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 31)
    - Graduation Address to the Graduate of Suffolk University Law School, Boston, MA, June 5, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 32)
    - "Fighting Corruption and Mismanagement: A 'Must' for Better and More Efficient Government," Annual Dinner of the Better Government Association, Chicago, IL, June 20, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 33)
    - "Toward a Revitalization of Public Service," Taft Institute Seminar on American Government and Politics, Marywood College, Scranton, PA, July 1, 1988 (Box 710, Folder 34)
  - Pre-Directorship Institute of Politics Research, 2.
    Prior to Thornburgh's arrival as Director of the Institute of Politics in June 1987, he methodically researched IOP's history, policies, and programs to enable him, as the adage states, to "hit the ground running." Many of these materials were prepared for Thornburgh by Rick Stafford (RAS), who had served in the Thornburgh Gubernatorial administration. Stafford put together briefing binders, status reports and work plans which include the history of IOP and analyze new directions the Institute could take under Thornburgh's leadership. Also included are Thornburgh's notes on IOP, correspondence related to his job search, as well as potential reorganization plans for IOP.
    - History reports, articles and publication listings, 1972-1987 (Box 710, Folder 35)
    - Thornburgh's post-governorship job search, October, 1986-January, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 36)
    - Thornburgh's "chron" file, including clippings and correspondence, January 15-May 7, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 37)
    - Thornburgh's notes in preparation for directorship of IOP, February-July, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 38)
    - IOP briefing binder on programs, administration and tasks, prepared by Rick Stafford, February 24, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 39)
    - IOP briefing binder, prepared by Rick Stafford, with background materials and Harvard articles, February, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 40)
    - Rick Stafford's report on the IOP, February 23, 1987 (Box 710, Folder 41)
    - Clippings, notes, correspondence and schedules in preparation for directorship, February-July, 1987 (Box 711, Folder 1)
    - IOP work plan for Thornburgh, prepared by Rick Stafford, May 4, 1987 (Box 711, Folder 2)
    - IOP reorganization plan: memo by assistant director Mary McTigue, May 28, 1987 (Box 711, Folder 3)
    - IOP Status report of important tasks for director, prepared by Rick Stafford, June 4, 1987 (Box 711, Folder 4)
  - News Releases, 3.
    The news releases issued by the Institute of Politics (IOP) during Thornburgh's year as Director are arranged here in chronological order from 1987-1988. These releases pertain both to Thornburgh and others more generally to IOP events. All have been digitized and are available here online.
    - 1987-1988 (Box 711, Folder 5)
      - Pennsylvania Governor to head Harvard's Institute of Politics, January 15, 1987; 1.
      - Institute of Politics celebrates 20th anniversary: national and international political leaders to analyze American politics, May 5, 1987; 2.
      - Former Pennsylvania Governor Dick Thornburgh today assumes post as Director of the Institute of Politics (IOP) at Harvard's John F. Kennedy School of Government, June 1, 1987; 3.
      - Governor Dick Thornburgh today announced the selection of four Fellows who will be in residence at the Institute this fall, August 26, 1987; 4.
      - Governor Dick Thornburgh today announced the appointment of Thelma Duggin, formerly a special assistant to the President, as a resident Fellow for the fall term, September 9, 1987; 5.
      - Governor Dick Thornburgh today announced the selection of five persons with strong backgrounds in elective politics to serve as resident Fellows of the Institute for the spring semester, January 13, 1988; 6.
      - Linda Starnes, a key staffer at the Institute of Politics, has been elected president of the Harvard Business School Partners Club, with quotation by Institute director Governor Thornburgh, January 14, 1988; 7.
      - Forty Harvard undergraduates have been granted summer stipend or summer research awards by the Institute of Politics (IOP), Director Dick Thornburgh announced, May 20, 1988; 8.
  - Harvard University, John F. Kennedy School of Government, and Institute of Politics Files, 4.
    These file relate to all three "institutions" with which Thornburgh was associated and are in four relevant sections: Harvard materials are arranged in a general chronological order and include news articles, newsletters and Harvard publications, as well as information on major Harvard "personalities" in preparation for meetings.
    John F. Kennedy School of Government (JFK School) materials deal with information from the 50th anniversary of the school, curricula reviews and information, possible courses of interest to Thornburgh, and memoranda from Graham Allison, dean of the Kennedy School.
    Institute of Politics (IOP) administration and organization files include information on budget, fundraising, organization of the office's materials, concept papers on various political topics, information on prospective visiting fellows, materials from committees, and IOP publications and brochures.
    Files from the Institute of Politics (IOP) programs, conferences, and workshops are arranged in a general chronological order and include materials on those in which Thornburgh participated or helped plan. Examples include "The Public, the Soviet and Nuclear Arms Conference," "Latin American Debt Conference," " Program for Newly-Elected Members of Congress," and the "ARCO Forum on Public Affairs." Please note that the archives include a complete set of the ARCO Forum posters.
    - Harvard University Material
      - Harvard personalities: briefing sheets for meetings, June, 1987 (Box 711, Folder 6)
      - Center for Business and Government, Public and Private Careers Project, uniting public and private sectors to solve U.S.'s major problems, August-December, 1987 (Box 711, Folder 7)
      - Center for Business and Government, Privatization Study Group, for privatization of state-owned enterprises, August, 1987-January, 1988 (Box 711, Folder 8)
      - Harvard Political Review, Spring, 1987-November, 1988 (Box 711, Folder 9)
      - Guidebook to Harvard University, the Crimson Key Society's 350th Anniversary Edition, published by the President and Fellows of Harvard College, 1986 (Box 711, Folder 10)
      - Miscellaneous Harvard publications, including Update, State, Local and Intergovernmental Report, and Harvard Magazine, 1986-1988 (Box 711, Folder 11)
      - Articles and news clippings, 1987-1988 (Box 711, Folder 12)
      - "Future of IOP, politics bright, says new director Thornburgh," Harvard University Gazette article, June 11, 1987 (Box 711, Folder 13)
    - John F. Kennedy School of Government Material
      - "50 years" anniversary newsletter and published book, 1986 (Box 711, Folder 14)
      - "From Harrisburg to Harvard: Richard Thornburgh welcomed to IOP," John F. Kennedy School of Government Bulletin article, Spring, 1987 (Box 711, Folder 15)
      - John F. Kennedy School of Government Bulletin, Spring-Summer, 1988 (Box 711, Folder 16)
      - Public Opinion, Politics and the Press, course taught by Gary Orren at the KSG, memoranda on development and syllabus, July-October, 1987 (Box 711, Folder 17)
      - Architectural information on JFK/IOP building, sent by Sheila Sheridan, director of special projects and construction, 1986 (Box 711, Folder 18)
      - Allison, Graham, dean of the John F. Kennedy School of Government, memoranda to Thornburgh, July, 1987-March, 1988 (Box 711, Folder 19)
      - Curriculum review, committee to review the School's degree programs and all courses offered for credit, November, 1987-January, 1988 (Box 711, Folder 20)
      - Fundraising "flap", November, 1987 (Box 711, Folder 21)
      - Catalogue of programs and courses of study, 1987-1988 (Box 711, Folder 22)
    - Institute of Politics Administration and Organization Files
      - General and miscellaneous clippings, memoranda, correspondence, and memorabilia, February, 1986-April, 1988 (Box 711, Folder 23)
      - Budget, notes, memoranda and calculations, 1987-1988 (Box 711, Folder 24)
      - Letter to and research on Walter Annenberg, chairman of Triangle Publications and president of the Annenberg Fund, in effort to receive funding, December, 1987-May, 1988 (Box 711, Folder 25)
      - Records Management report on the assessment and organization of IOP files and materials, by Nancy Watson, consultant to director Thornburgh, May-September, 1987 (Box 711, Folder 26)
      - Mailing lists, 1987-1988 (Box 711, Folder 27)
      - Concept papers on topics related to politics, 1987-1988 (Box 711, Folder 28)
      - Fellows: notes, memoranda and correspondence to, from, and about visiting Fellows, 1987-1988 (Box 711, Folder 29)
      - Prospective Fellows for Fall term 1987: schedules, plans and notes, 1986-1987 (Box 712, Folder 1)
      - Visiting Fellows for Spring term 1988: schedules, correspondence, plans and notes, October, 1987-February, 1988 (Box 712, Folder 2)
      - Visiting Fellows for Fall term 1988: schedules, correspondence, plans and notes, May-August, 1988 (Box 712, Folder 3)
      - Fellows' Orientation Week program and information packet, September 14-18, 1987 (Box 712, Folder 4)
      - Fellows: "pool" of possible candidates, August, 1987 (Box 712, Folder 5)
      - Advisory Committee on Women in Politics, October-November, 1988 (Box 712, Folder 6)
      - Student Advisory Committee (SAC): student programs binder and reports on spring semester 1988, June 14, 1988 (Box 712, Folder 7)
      - Student Advisory Committee (SAC): recommendation letters, correspondence to and from Thornburgh, internal committee correspondence, and memoranda, 1987-1988 (Box 712, Folder 8)
      - Student Advisory Committee (SAC): study groups, participants, topics, leaders, and evaluations, 1987-1988 (Box 712, Folder 9)
      - Student Advisory Committee (SAC): externships, lists of extern match-ups, and coordination of opportunities for students, 1988 (Box 712, Folder 10)
      - Student Advisory Committee (SAC): internships and job opportunities for undergraduates, 1987 (Box 712, Folder 11)
      - Student Advisory Committee (SAC): Summer in Washington Program for undergraduates and newsletters regarding events, Summer, 1988 (Box 712, Folder 12)
      - Student Advisory Committee (SAC): Summer stipends awards program, recipient list, and news releases, Summer, 1988 (Box 712, Folder 13)
      - Student Advisory Committee (SAC): Summer in Boston program, meetings, and activity lists, Summer, 1987 (Box 712, Folder 14)
      - Student Advisory Committee (SAC): Summer in Boston program, application for coordinator position, and newsletters with activities information, Summer, 1988 (Box 712, Folder 15)
      - Student Advisory Committee (SAC): Students' resumes, recommendation letters, graduates' forwarding address lists, and notes, 1988 (Box 712, Folder 16)
      - Senior Advisory Committee: meeting binder, November 30, 1987 (Box 712, Folder 17)
      - Senior Advisory Committee: contact lists and correspondence, July, 1987-July, 1988 (Box 712, Folder 18)
      - Senior Advisory Committee: letter from Thornburgh requesting a leave of absence to serve as U.S. Attorney General, August 11, 1988 (Box 712, Folder 19)
      - Newsletters and related correspondence, November, 1987-Winter, 1988 (Box 712, Folder 20)
      - What's Happening newsletter, October-December, 1987 (Box 712, Folder 21)
      - Publications and brochures, includes 25th anniversary booklet, sent to Thornburgh while Attorney General, 1987-1991 (Box 712, Folder 22)
      - Proceedings, 1966-1988 (Box 712, Folder 23)